William Helfand collection of medical ephemera
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
William Helfand collection of medical ephemera
1817-2007
Pam Coll 8
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
5
(16 three-ring albums and 2 archives boxes one of which is legal size)
The collection contains printed ephemera related to medicine and pharmacy either arranged in albums by William Helfand or donated in loose form. These include trade cards (some on marijuana and street drugs), postcards, advertisements in various formats for patent medicines and devices, advertisements for cancer cures, playing cards, cards of famous scientists and physicians, stock certificates for pharmaceutical companies, photographs of old pharmacies, pharmacy prescription envelopes, stereoscopic photographs, and more.
Helfand, William H.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William Helfand.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Advertising -- Medicine; AIDS (Disease); Asthma -- Treatment; Cancer -- Treatment; Cigarettes -- Great Britain; Deafness; Dentists; Drugs of abuse; Drugstores -- Denmark; Drugstores -- Great Britain; Drugstores -- Sweden; Drugstores -- United States; Electricity in medicine; Hay fever -- Treatment; Health insurance -- Great Britain; Health insurance -- United States; Marijuana; Medicine -- History; Medicine shows; Patent medicines; Pharmacists; Pharmacy colleges; Physicians; Quacks and quackery; Trusses; Albums; Advertising cards; Ephemera (general object genre); Invitations; Playing cards; Photographs; Postcards; Postage stamps; Radio scripts; Slides; Stereoscopic photographs; Stock certificates; Trade cards (advertising); Haggard, Howard Wilcox, 1891-1959; Beecham's Pills (Firm); Elliman, Sons & Co; J. C. Eno Ltd
- Albums, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The albums are three ring binders with medical ephemera arranged in partitioned plastic pages by William Helfand. The order within each notebook has been retained. The numbering of the notebooks has been changed by the archivist.
  - Album 1: Trading Cards on "drug wars," AIDS, and marijuana; playing cards on medical themes (Volume 1)
    Cards are in plastic sleeves, six to a page. Formerly notebook 119.
    - "Drug Wars Trading Cards", 1991
      37 cards, satirizing people and events. Text by Paul Brancato and Bob Callahan, art by Salim Yaqub. Published by Eclipse Enterprises, Forestville, California, copyright 1991.
    - "AIDS Awareness: People With AIDS" trading cards, 1993
      72 cards and 3 stickers. Cards depict people with AIDS, AIDS activists, groups supporting AIDS awareness, and information about AIDS. Text by William Livingstone, art by Charles Hiscock, published by Eclipse Enterprises, Forestville, California, copyright 1993.
    - "Marijuana Stories" trading cards, 1996
      109 cards with photographs and descriptions of the different varieties of hemp around the world. Various photographers. Published by InLine, Chestnut Publications, copyright 1996.
    - Playing cards on medical themes
      Includes various sets of playing cards: a set featuring classic travel and advertising posters; miscellaneous cards advertising drug stores or medicines; set titled, "Pioneers in Medicine Card Game" by U.S. Games Systems, Inc, Stamford Connecticut, copyright 1991; German cards on great doctors by Fevarin; set of cards on first aid by the National Safety Council, Chicago, Illinois, copyright 1981; set of medical joke cards from the 1950s or 1960s; a French set on anti-smoking by the Association Regionale de Cardiologie; "Le Jeu des Medecins Midi-Pyrenees," by Pinozac published by Baptiste Paul Grimaud, Paris; set on AIDS by the State of Florida Department of Health and Rehabilitative Services; sets of cards titled "Death on Drugs Playing Cards" and "Death Cigarette Playing Cards," both featuring skeletons, by Death Playing Cards, Alamo, California.
  - Album 2: Advertisements for cancer "cures" and trusses, late 19th century-early 20th century (Volume 2)
    Broadsides, advertising letters, and brochures promoting "cures" for cancer without surgery, and trusses for ruptures. Most are American. There are a few later items including one pamphlet by the American Cancer Society. On appliances for ruptures, see also Box 2, Folders 3-8.
  - Album 3: "Ephemera Savants" -- trading cards and other pieces, chiefly showing prominent physicians and scientists, mostly 20th century (Volume 3)
    Series of illustrated cards featuring mainly famous Historical physicians and scientists.
    - Cards featuring famous scientists and physicians
      Series of cards featuring scientists and physicians distributed by: various chocolate makers, the French publishing house Fernand Nathan, Liebig's Extract of Meat (many cards chiefly French and Italian), Maltine, the Arlington Chemical Company (Liquid Peptinoids); and European cigarette companies. The same publishing company created cards for several chocolatiers. One set of cards for a chocolate maker contained first aid instructions on the back. Of note are a series of bookmarks published by Wallace Laboratories, New Brunswick, N.J., makers of the anti-anxiety drug Miltown.
    - Stamps, both postal and non-postal
      Set of stamps issued by the Chicago Heart Association in 1952; stamps by Maltzym, a drug company; a series on "Breakthroughs in Modern Medicine issued by Bhutan," and various other stamps.
    - Set of history of medicine cards
      Published by Panarizon Publishing Corp in 1979-1980, the 42 large-format cards cover ancient false teeth to heart transplants. Includes patent medicines and medicine shows, Margaret Sanger, nursing homes, and various episodes in public health.
  - Album 4: Postcards and cards on medical subjects, 20th century (Volume 4)
    General
    Some items were removed before the library received the album.
    - Postcards, mostly humorous
      Includes postcards advertising products, photographs of pharmacies, cartoons about the advent of National Health Insurance in Great Britain, American political satire, and others. In English, French, German, and Spanish.
    - Cards on doctors, nurses, and chemists and their families
      For example, there are cards for Mr. Drug the Doctor, Mrs. Drug the Doctor's Wife, Miss Drug the Doctor's Daughter, and Master Drug the Doctor's Son. These cards could be used in a game, but they are not standard playing cards. They are mostly British. Some cards have been removed from the album before its donation. Of interest is a card filed along with the doctor families for a Jewish mohel in Portland, Maine, who claims to be an "Antiseptic Specialist."
    - Cards on healing saints, especially Cosmos and Damian
    - Cards on recreational drugs
      One set of 36 cards, titled "Dope Fiends," features artistic covers from 1940s-1960s novels about drugs (for example, Black Opium. The descriptions provide the name of the artist and information about the book. Another set published by the Las Vegas Township Constable's Office, comes with directions for a game, "Kid's War Against Drugs"
    - Small cards on bandaging and first aid
      Some are issued by British cigarette brands such as Mitchell's Cigarettes and Wills's Cigarettes.
    - Plastic telephone cards advertising medicines, etc.
  - Album 5: Admission tickets, Invitations, programs, and announcement cards, 19th - 21st centuries (Volume 5)
    This volume is very miscellaneous. Some material was removed from this album prior to its donation.
    - Admission tickets
      These include admission as a patient to a hospital or clinic, invitations to various medical-related events such as an excursion to visit Bellevue Hospital in England, and invitations to attend lectures, meetings, and ceremonies of medical societies and schools.
    - Invitations
      Invitations to commemorative events, lectures, exhibits, meetings, and dinners. Some are addressed to William Helfand.
    - Programs
      Programs for meetings of societies, dedications, dinners, and other special events. See also dinner program in honor of Robert Koch in Box 2, Folder 1.
    - Announcements and advertisements
      Most are postcard size and advertise healers, products, and book dealers.
  - Album 6: Treatments for asthma, hay fever, and other bronchial complaints; remedies for deafness, early 19th century-1990s (Volume 6)
    - Advertisements for physicians and remedies for asthma, hay fever, and other bronchial complaints, early 19th century-1990s
      Advertisements in a variety of formats; letters, postcards, pamphlets, broadsides, clippings from magazines, stamps, and matchbook covers. Most are American and British and represent a variety of products. There are several questionnaires for patients to fill out before they are treated. A few of the companies are P. Harold Hayes, Buffalo, N.Y., who published The Hayes Bulletin; Frontier Asthma Company, Buffalo, N.Y.; The Blosser Company, Atlanta, Georgia; and the Carbolic Smoke Ball, London. Of note are a series of modern postcards for the National Asthma Campaign, UK, and by 3M Pharma for a French congress in pneumology in 1997.
    - Advertisements for remedies for deafness, 19th century-early 20th century.
      Included, among other companies, are several advertisements for George P. Way, Detroit, Michigan; and for the Mears Ear Phone Co., New York. There is an older advertisement for Dr. McNair's Acoustic Oil. See also Box 1, folder 21.
  - Album 7: Advertisements for electric belts other electro-medical apparatus, mostly late 19th century (Volume 7)
    Advertisements for electromagnetic appliances for medical use. The majority are for Harness' Electropathic Belt and Harness' Electric Corset; and the Medical Battery Co., Ltd., London, to be obtained at the Electropathic & Zander Institute. Among other advertisers of electromedical products in Britain, France, and America are Dr. Alfred Sanden, New York; Dr. Scott's Electric Flesh Brush, New York; Thomas E. Hooker galvanic apparatus, Wellington, Somerset: the Magneto-Electric Battery Co., London; Dr. Carter Moffat's Electric Body Belt; the VEEDEE for Vibratory Massage, London; Pulvermacher's Ltd., London; Dr. U. L. Girard, Paris; Jerome Kidder's Electro-Medical Apparatus; Dr. Lowder's Magneto-Electric Battery, London; Dr. B.-T. MacLaughlin, Paris; Darlow & Co., London. The volume also includes a British patent for the manufacture of plasters for medical purposes.
  - Album 8: Advertisements for Beecham's Pills, Elliman's Embrocation, and Eno's 'Fruit Salt', late 19th century-early 20th century (Volume 8)
    Advertisements in this album have come mostly from magazines. Beechams Pills, St. Helen's, Lancashire, England, England, was a cure-all especially for "bilious and nervous disorders." Items include a few games or amusements, as for example, "Beecham's Rosette Puzzle." There is also a receipt for the purchase of Beecham's Pills by a drug store in 1908. One racist advertisement features a black maid with the caption "What am good for the Missus am good for me."
    Elliman's Universal Embrocation or Elliman's Royal Embrocation were manufactured by Elliman and Sons & Co., Slough, England. The ads, including seven postcards, featured sports and especially horses and riding. Elliman's Universal Embrocation was said to provide relief from rheumatism and other aches and pains. Elliman's Royal Embrocation was used "for Horses, Cattle, and Dogs."
    Eno's 'Fruit Salt,' "the World-Famous Effervescent Saline," was prepared by J.C. Eno, Ltd, in London. It was said to purify the blood and cure stomach ailments as well as a variety of other ills.
  - Album 9: Medical politics; radio talks on history of medicine; miscellany, 1817, 1914-ca. 1950 (Volume 9)
    - Pamphlets and advertisements against the Wagner-Murray-Dingell Bills, mostly 1945-1946
      Pamphlets, several including cartoons, by organized medicine and dentistry against President Truman's national health care plan. The plan is portrayed as "socialized medicine," "political medicine," and "strictly un-American."
    - Other medical politics
      Program of the First Annual Convention of the United Medicine Manufacturers of America, intended "to formulate ways and means to protect the Ready Packaged Medicine Industry," no date; two pamphlets of the National League for Medical Freedom opposing "medical monopoly," 1911 and no date; pamphlet titled "The Inoculation Maniac," ca. 1916, by the California Anti-Vivisection Society, ca. 1915; cartoon on "The War on Quackery"; broadside "Médecins Français!" calling upon physicians to aid the Comité National des Médecins Français to combat insurrection in Algeria, no date.
    - Radio talks on "Devils, Drugs and Doctors," by Howard W. Haggard, Yale University, 1931
      These radio talks were broadcast over CBS in 1931 and sponsored by Eastman Kodak Company. The six pamphlets provide the text of the talks. Haggard was then associate professor of physiology at Yale, and an avid historian of medicine. He was the author of Devils, drugs, and doctors: the story of the science of healing from medicine-man to doctor (New York: Harper and Brothers, 1929).
    - Miscellany, 1817
      Two small broadsides related to a meeting of the subscribers of the Bridgnorth Dispensary after the resignation of Mr. Lampet, one of the surgeons at the dispensary, 1817.
  - Album 10: Commemorative postal stamps, stock certificates; redeemable coupons; and U.S. forms for the use of opium and alcohol in medicine, mostly 20th century (Volume 10)
    - Commemorative postage stamps
      Stamps commemorating health-related people and subjects. Most are U.S. They include official "First Day of Issue" pages on commemoratives issued by the U.S. Postal Service as well as full sheets of stamps. Among the persons are Harvey W. Wiley, Harvey Cushing, Joseph Priestley, Charles Drew, and George Papanicolaou. Among subjects are pharmacy, chemistry, osteopathic medicine, health research, and alcoholism.
    - Stock certificates related to pharmacy
      These include shares in drug stores and drug companies, several state certificates registering pharmacies, and one certificate stating that a student had attended lectures at University College, Nottingham. See Box 1, Folders 1-4 for more stock certificates.
    - Coupons issued by apothecaries, spas, etc.
      Coupons are small (ca. 6x9 cm.), mostly German, attractively designed, and dating from the mid-nineteenth to early twentieth century. Each has a monetary unit in pfennigs or marks. Among the coupons is a one dollar "bond" for the Missionary Medical College for Women in Vellore, India.
    - Official U.S. forms for drug stores' obtaining opium, or for use by physicians prescribing alcohol during Prohibition, 1913-1928
      Permission and tax forms for importing and dispensing opium and opium products, according to a law of 1914. Also in this volume are filled examples of "Prescription Blank - National Prohibition Act." Under Prohibition, physicians were required to fill out a form every time they prescribed alcohol as a medication.
  - Album 11: Images and slides on the "medicine show" (Volume 11)
    Includes copies of photographs of medicine show scenes from the 19th and early 20th centuries, copies of advertisements for Indian-themed products, images and ephemera related to modern re-creations of medicine shows, and correspondence of William H. Helfand on the medicine show exhibit at the Medical Historical Library, Yale, in 1984. There is material in the album on the Kickapoo Indian Medicine Co. (New Haven) and the Oregon Indian Medicine Co. among others. Of note are copies of forms for renting halls or lots for a medicine show to visit a town. Formerly Vol. 89
  - Album 12: Prescription envelopes (Receptkuverter) from Swedish and other Nordic pharmacies, early 20th century - 1990s (Volume 12)
    Small envelopes, about 8x12 cm., for the return of prescriptions, given by pharmacies to customers. The entire front cover was illustrated, often by an image of the pharmacy, but sometimes by artistic designs. Most of the envelopes in the album are from Sweden but a number are from other Nordic counties (Norway, Denmark, Finland, Iceland). The most recent envelopes are from the 1980s and 1990s.
  - Album 13: Nordic prescription envelopes, early 20th century-1999 (Volume 13)
    Approximate size of covers is 8x12 cm.
  - Album 14: Nordic prescription envelopes, 20th century (Volume 14)
    Swedish and other Nordic apothecary envelopes with attractive designs to hold customer prescriptions after they were filled. Some feature cartoon jokes involving a customer and a pharmacist.
  - Album 15: Prescription envelopes and envelopes for patent medicine samples, United States, Great Britain, and other countries, mostly 20th century (Volume 15)
    The British prescription envelopes typically have the patient's name written on the envelope. The envelopes that advertise a product, and once contained a product sample, are mostly American. Among these are headache cures, corn removers, and court plasters. One envelope contains a personal folding cup from the Sanitary Drinking Cup Co., Chicago. In the United Sates, pharmacists retained the prescriptions they filled.
  - Album 16: Miscellany (Volume 16)
    Engraving of Dr. Samuel B. Collins, advertisements for his "opium antidote" and other ephemera; portrait photograph of Saide B. Collins; more prescription envelopes; more bookplates; match covers; French cards of famous scientists published by Fernand Nathan; and other advertisements.
- Loose material in boxes, Series II
  These materials were donated in folders or in loose form and arranged by the archivist.
  - Box 1: Stock certificates for drug companies; photographs of pharmacies and pharmacy schools; miscellany
    This loose material has been arranged by the archivist.
    - Stock certificates for drug companies, A-D, 1906-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Stock certificates for drug or drugstore companies, for example, Rexall. Includes many more obscure companies. Arranged by company name.
    - Stock certificates for drug companies, E-J, 1920-1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Stock certificates for drug companies, K-P, 1916-1978 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Stock certificates for drug companies, Q-Z, 1923-1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of pharmacies (large size sleeves), late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 5)
      These are posed professional photographs of the exterior or interior of American pharmacies. Usually the photographs include the proprietor and sometimes staff and customers. Most photographs are contemporary and usually the store is identified.
    - Photographs of pharmacies (medium size), late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes a British and a French pharmacy. Some of these photographs are not identified.
    - Photographs of pharmacies (small size), late19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Photographs: Brooklyn College of Pharmacy, 1893, 1920s (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The 1893 photograph is of a class visit to the Seabury Pharmaceutical Laboratory. Students and instructors are seated on benches. There are four women and one African-American among them. The 1920s photos show a sports team, a laboratory, pharmaceutical preparations, and a lecture hall.
    - Photographs: Other pharmacy schools, 1889, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Faculty of Columbia College of Pharmacy, 1889; band "Pharmaceutican" from the pharmacy school at University of Nebraska, 1928. The latter includes an African American member.
    - Photographs: Advertising of products, late 19th century-early twentieth century (Box 1, Folder 10)
      One photo shows a window advertisement for "Celery King"; another shows an advertisement painted on a barn for Dr. Pierce, Buffalo, "Cures Weak Women"; and a third shows a man, posed with one foot on a box from Keystone Drug Co., South Boston, holding up a bottle of medicine.
    - Photographs: Miscellaneous medicine (small size), late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Stereoscopic views: Pharmacy, late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Incudes T.H. Eaton Drug Co., Toronto. Most of the stereoscopic views were intended to entertain a general audience, rather than promote a specific pharmacy. Several of the views are intended to be humorous.
    - Stereoscopic views: Medicine, late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Stereoscopic views: Dentistry, late 19th century-early 20th century (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Stereoscopic views: World War I, 1914-1918 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Prohibition era carton for Gibson's Pure Rye Whiskey "For Medical Purposes Only" (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Carton for Chief Two Moon Bitter Oil Laxative, Waterbury, Conn. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Manufactured by Chief Two Moon Herb Co., Waterbury, Conn.
    - Cardboard advertisement for Pilules Vegetales Morison, D'Arthaud-Moulin (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Lactopeptine Calendar, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Calendar is "Compliments of Lactopeptine, New York Pharmacal Association, Yonkers, N.Y." It begins in October 1902 and ends September 1903. Each month features a famous historical physician.
    - F. L. Durkee, Avon, New York, Foot and arch correction (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Broadside. "Continuing the so-called Dr. Locke method of foot and arch correction."
    - Advertisements on remedies for hearing loss (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Broadsides and pamphlets by Gem Ear-Phone Co., George P. Way, the Mega Ear Phone, and George E. Coutant, M.D.
    - Eckman Manufacturing Co., Philadelphia, 1906-1912 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Remedies for tuberculosis, bronchitis, and other ailments of the lungs.
    - Dr. Hart's Vegetable Extract, ca. 1853 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      This eight-page brochure contains testimonials, the latest of which was dated 1853. The Vegetable-Extract was intended for "Epilepsy, or Falling Sickness" and also spasms, convulsions, and hysteria. S. M. Hart, M.D. lived in New York.
    - "Highgate Dispensary" - brochure promoting vaccination, ca. 1821 (Box 1, Folder 24)
      Contains information on the organization of the dispensary, patients admitted, and subscribers.
    - Constable of Bangor Borough, Report to the Judges of Northampton County on inspection of vendors of liquors, 1887 October 10 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Printed form filled out by David Parsons, Constable, listing the licensed places for vending liquors. Bangor Borough is in Pennsylvania.
    - Tome V. -- Armes et Services Divers. Chapitre XXV. Le Service de Sante (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Collectors' issue of postcards illustrating the costumes of health officers in the Napoleonic era.
  - Box 2: Additional loose ephemera
    - Program for a dinner in honor of Robert Koch, New York, 1908 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - "Know Yourself," phrenology examination of a child by J. Boyd, ca. 1843 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Printed one-page form with the printed date 1843. The name of the client and numbers are written in ink for the various "affective facultie" and "intellectual faculties."
    - Rupture appliances: Brooks Rupture Appliance Co., Marshall, Mich., 1940 and undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Two pamphlets and a "Trial Order Form." The pamphlets are titled Brooks' Rupture Appliance Greatest Discovery & Invention of the Twentieth Century. One is dated 1940; the other appears to be earlier.
    - Rupture appliances: Brooks Appliance Co., Ltd., London, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      This the London Branch of Brooks Appliance Co., Marshall, Mich. The folder contains a full-page advertisement from The Humorist, June 2, 1923.
    - Rupture appliances; Chas. Cluthe and Sons, Bloomfield, N.J., early 20th century (Box 2, Folder 5)